putnam.com 2013-08-11

# Putnam Investments: Privacy policy

|   | 

## Putnam privacy policy

  *   * Putnam's commitment to confidentiality 

In order to conduct business with our shareholders, we must obtain certain personal information such as account holders' names, addresses, Social Security numbers, and dates of birth. Using this information, we are able to maintain accurate records of accounts and transactions. 

It is our policy to protect the confidentiality of our shareholder information, whether or not a shareholder currently owns shares of our funds. In particular, it is our policy not to sell information about you or your accounts to outside marketing firms. We have safeguards in place designed to prevent unauthorized access to our computer systems and procedures to protect personal information from unauthorized use. 

Under certain circumstances, we do share information with outside vendors who provide services to us, such as mailing and proxy solicitation. In those cases, the firms with whom we do business enter into confidentiality agreements with us, and we limit the information we provide them to only what is necessary to process transactions and perform other services related to your shareholder account. It is also our policy to share account information with your financial advisor, if you've provided us with information about your advisor and that person is listed on your Putnam account. 

If you would like clarification about our confidentiality policies or have any questions or concerns, please don't hesitate to contact us at 1-800-225-1581, Monday through Friday, 8:00 a.m. to 8:00 p.m. Eastern Time. 

  * User confidential information/privacy 

User recognizes that User's use of Putnam Electronic Services or any online securities transaction system, Web-based or otherwise, may involve the transmission to User of information that may be considered personal financial information, including but not limited to the identity and number of shares that User trades and the net dollar price for the shares. User consents to the transmission by electronic means of such information through any system, service, or product named or referred to in the preceding sentence; such consent shall be effective at all times that User uses any such system, service, or product. However, whenever User provides a login and password, the site entered will be a secure site. 

Putnam will not release information about User or User's Putnam accounts except as permitted by law. For example, Putnam may release this information if one of the following conditions is met: 

    * Putnam receives User's prior written consent.
    * Putnam believes the recipient to be User or User's authorized representative.
    * Putnam is required by law to release information to the recipient.

  * Types of personal information collected on each site 

Putnam collects the information needed to process a User's login and any of the User's online requests on each of its sites. This information may include the following, by site: 

    * Putnam Investments: Name, postal address, email address, and Social Security number.
    * Shareholders: Name, postal address, email address, Social Security number, telephone number, and fax number.
    * Financial Advisor: Name, postal address, email address, Social Security number, telephone number, fax number, and account numbers.
    * Institutional Investors: None
    * Retirement Plan Participants: Name, postal address, email address, Social Security number, telephone number, and fax number.

Putnam does not collect personal information unless the User provides it to us. 

  * Other information collected 

If an individual enters our secured section through use of an ID, we already have on file their name, address, and their account information. We time-stamp all incoming sessions, and we collect the IP, domain name, session duration, transactions made, and pages viewed. Technical information (such as IP address, operating system, and session ID) is collected in addition to data the User saves in an online calculator or investment tool, as well as transaction requests, such as requests for changes to account options. 

  * What are cookies and how does Putnam use them? 

A cookie is a small text file created by a Web server and stored on a User's computer. Cookies are used to provide User-side Web site customization, help Putnam analyze our Web page flow, measure promotional effectiveness, and offer certain features that are only available through the use of a "cookie." 

Putnam uses login ID cookies to save customer login information. 

Putnam also uses temporary session cookies on all of its secure Web sites to store relevant session content such as an assigned User ID, so you can move between areas of a secure site. 

If your browser informs you that we are trying to set a cookie, you may decline our cookies, although in that case you may not be able to use certain features on the Web site. 

  * What will happen if you disable cookies 

Putnam uses cookies to save customer login information. If a customer chooses to change Web browser settings to disable or not accept the cookies, it may affect certain features on the Web site. 

  * How each site collects information 

    * Putnam Investments: Information is collected via the Contact Us form.
    * Shareholders: Information is collected via forms such as the Contact Us, Address Change, Mailing Options, Account Options, and Update Profile.
    * Financial Advisor: Information is collected via forms such as Customize Activity Alerts, Address Change, Literature Updates and Order, Account Options, and Update Profile.
    * Institutional Investors: None
    * Retirement Plan Participants: Information is collected via forms such as the Allocation Change form and the Deferral Change form.

  * How Putnam uses any information collected 

Putnam will only use information about User and User's Putnam accounts to help us better serve User's investment needs, respond to User requests or inquiries, or to suggest Putnam services or educational materials that may be of interest to User. Information collected is used for internal purposes only and is not shared with third parties. 

  * Does Putnam share information with third parties? 

Putnam does not give or sell any information about User or Users Putnam accounts to any other company, individual, or group except as permitted by law. For example, we may share information with outside vendors that provide services to us, pursuant to a confidentiality agreement. 

However, for your convenience, this site contains links to other Internet sites ("third-party sites") that are not maintained by Putnam. For example, we provide a link to "Save Online," which is hosted and provided by Time Inc. New Media. The personal information you provide to "Save Online" is not controlled by Putnam. In addition, we provide a link to the Hartford Life Insurance site, which is provided and hosted by Hartford Life Insurance. Putnam is not responsible for the content of those sites. We urge you to read the privacy and security policies of Save Online, Hartford Life Insurance, and any other external sites before providing your personal information to these sites. 

  * Ways you can control the information collected about you 

Putnam may from time to time send you via email, information regarding new products and services. You may change your personal information at any time by calling Putnam's toll-free numbers or by completing an online Change Address form or Update User Profile form for each of our sites: 

    * Shareholders: call 1-800-563-3665 or click on the "Address change" link on the "My Accounts" page or the "Update Profile" link on the Individual Investors home page.
    * Retirement participants: Call your plan's toll-free number.
    * Institutional investors: Call 1-888-4-PUTNAM (1-888-478-8626).
    * Financial advisors: Change your clients' information by calling 1-800-362-6061 or clicking on the "Address change" link on the "Accounts/Mutual Funds & 529" page.
